BETH: An individual with autism
who is anxious and struggling to
contain their own behaviour may not
be able to control their anxiety
and that behaviour might cause them
to develop more extreme behaviours.
JOE: Stimming is often very enjoyable
can be a good way for an individual with
autism to reduce stress and anxiety.
However, stimming can sometimes
cause self-injury, such as,
head-banging or scratching.
If this behaviour becomes in some way
unsafe, the individual needs to be
support them to stop or modify the
behaviour or reduce their reliance on it.
BETH: Maybe their senses are being
overloaded more than usual or maybe
they feel pain and can’t control it.
If the behaviour of the individual
cannot be de-escalated by the
usual strategies, then light
physical guidance may be needed.
JOE: If they are hitting themselves,
gently moving their hand away may help.
If they are head banging, putting a
pillow or cushion between them and the
hard object will help to prevent further
damage to themselves and the object.
Providing pain killers for physical pain
if prescribed can help to remove the
stress of pain and removing them to a room
where they can’t easily inflict physical
injury to themselves can mean there are
less danger from things around them.
BETH: If a risk of serious harm exists,
then a specialist may suggest more
physical restraints such as helmets,
gloves and arm restraints, which
can reduce the sensory experience
and frequency, as well as the harm.
But these should only be used in
emergencies as they don’t address
the cause of the behaviour just
alleviate the potential injury.
JOE: When a behaviour becomes so extreme
that it causes injury to an individual or
others it is a great cause for concern.
When an individual is engaged in an
active, disruptive stage of a behaviour,
such as showing aggression or anger,
the focus should be on the safety of
the individual and those around them.